<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE refentry PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd" [
				  
<!ENTITY % globalentities SYSTEM '../entities/global.entities'> %globalentities;
]>
<refentry id="mount.cifs.8">

<refmeta>
	<refentrytitle>mount.cifs</refentrytitle>
	<manvolnum>8</manvolnum>
</refmeta>


<refnamediv>
	<refname>mount.cifs</refname>
	<refpurpose>mount unter Verwendung des Common Internet File System (CIFS)</refpurpose>
</refnamediv>

<refsynopsisdiv>
	<cmdsynopsis>

		<command>mount.cifs</command>
		<arg choice="req">service</arg>	
		<arg choice="req">mount-Punkt</arg>	
		<arg choice="opt">-o Optionen</arg>	
	</cmdsynopsis>
</refsynopsisdiv>

<refsect1>
	<title>BESCHREIBUNG</title>

	<para>Dieses Werkzeug ist Teil der <citerefentry><refentrytitle>Samba</refentrytitle>
	<manvolnum>7</manvolnum></citerefentry>-Suite.</para>

	<para>mount.cifs bindet ein Linux CIFS Dateisystem ein. Es wird üblicherweise indirekt
	aufgerufen, mittels des Befehls
	<citerefentry><refentrytitle>mount</refentrytitle><manvolnum>8</manvolnum></citerefentry>
	und der Option "-t cifs". Dieser Befehl funktioniert nur unter Linux, und der Kernel muß
	das CIFS-Dateisystem unterstützen. Das CIFS-Protokoll ist der Nachfolger des SMB-Protokolls
	und wird von den meisten Windows-Servern unterstützt, von vielen anderen kommerziellen Servern
	und NAS-Einrichtungen ebenso wie von dem populären Open-Source-Server Samba.
	</para>

	<para>
	Das Werkzeug mount.cifs hängt den UNC-Namen (exportierte Netzwerk-Ressource) an das
	lokale Verzeichnis <emphasis>mount-Punkt</emphasis> an. Es ist möglich, den Modus für
	mount.cifs auf setuid root zu setzen, um nicht-root-Benutzern zu erlauben, Verzeichnisse
	einzubinden, zu denen sie Schreibberechtigungen besitzen.
	</para>

	<para>
	Optionen für <emphasis>mount.cifs</emphasis> werden als eine List von durch Kommas getrennten 
	Schlüssel=Wert Paaren angegeben. Es ist möglich, andere Optionen als die hier angegebenen
	zu senden, unter der Annahme, daß das CIFS-Dateisystem sie unterstützt.
	Nicht erkannte CIFS-mount-Optionen, die dem CIFS-VFS-Kernel-Code übergeben werden, werden
	im Kernel-Log protokolliert.
	</para>

	<para><emphasis>mount.cifs</emphasis> veranlaßt das CIFS-VFS dazu, einen Thread namens cifsd
	zu starten. Nach dem Einbinden/mounten läuft dieser weiter, bis die Einbindung der Ressource
	wieder gelöst wird (üblicherweise mittels umount).
	</para>

</refsect1>

<refsect1>
	<title>OPTIONEN</title>
	<variablelist>
		<varlistentry><term>user=<replaceable>arg</replaceable></term>

		<listitem><para>specifies the username to connect as. If
				this is not given, then the environment variable <emphasis>USER</emphasis> is used. This option can also take the
form "user%password" or "user/workgroup" or
"user/workgroup%password" to allow the password and workgroup
to be specified as part of the username.
		</para>

<note>
	<para>
	The cifs vfs accepts the parameter <parameter>user=</parameter>, or for users familiar with smbfs it accepts the longer form of the parameter <parameter>username=</parameter>.  Similarly the longer smbfs style parameter names may be accepted as synonyms for the shorter cifs parameters <parameter>pass=</parameter>,<parameter>dom=</parameter> and <parameter>cred=</parameter>.
	</para>
</note>

		</listitem>
	</varlistentry>

	<varlistentry><term>password=<replaceable>arg</replaceable></term>

		<listitem><para>specifies the CIFS password. If this
option is not given then the environment variable
<emphasis>PASSWD</emphasis> is used. If the password is not specified 
directly or indirectly via an argument to mount <emphasis>mount.cifs</emphasis> will prompt
for a password, unless the guest option is specified.
</para>

<para>Note that a password which contains the delimiter
character (i.e. a comma ',') will fail to be parsed correctly
on the command line.  However, the same password defined
in the PASSWD environment variable or via a credentials file (see
below) will be read correctly.
</para>
	</listitem></varlistentry>

	<varlistentry><term>credentials=<replaceable>filename</replaceable></term>

		<listitem><para>
				specifies a file that contains a username
				and/or password. The format of the file is:
			</para>

<programlisting>
		username=<replaceable>value</replaceable>
		password=<replaceable>value</replaceable>
</programlisting>
		
		<para>
This is preferred over having passwords in plaintext in a
shared file, such as <filename>/etc/fstab</filename>. Be sure to protect any
credentials file properly.
		</para>
	</listitem></varlistentry>

	<varlistentry>
		<term>uid=<replaceable>arg</replaceable></term>

		<listitem><para>sets the uid that will own all files on
	the mounted filesystem.
	It may be specified as either a username or a numeric uid.
	This parameter is ignored when the target server supports
	the CIFS Unix extensions.</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>

	<varlistentry>
		<term>gid=<replaceable>arg</replaceable></term>

		<listitem><para>sets the gid that will own all files on
the mounted filesystem.
It may be specified as either a groupname or a numeric 
gid. This parameter is ignored when the target server supports
the CIFS Unix extensions.
		</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>

	<varlistentry>
		<term>port=<replaceable>arg</replaceable></term>

		<listitem><para>sets the port number on the server to attempt to contact to negotiate
CIFS support.  If the CIFS server is not listening on this port or
if it is not specified, the default ports will be tried i.e. 
port 445 is tried and if no response then port 139 is tried.
		</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>

	<varlistentry>
		<term>file_mode=<replaceable>arg</replaceable></term>

		<listitem><para>If the server does not support the CIFS Unix extensions this
				overrides the default file mode.</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>

	<varlistentry>
		<term>dir_mode=<replaceable>arg</replaceable></term>

		<listitem><para>If the server does not support the CIFS Unix extensions this
				overrides the default mode for directories. </para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>

	<varlistentry>
		<term>ip=<replaceable>arg</replaceable></term>

		<listitem><para>sets the destination host or IP address.</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>

	<varlistentry>
		<term>domain=<replaceable>arg</replaceable></term>

		<listitem><para>sets the domain (workgroup) of the user </para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>

	<varlistentry>
		<term>guest</term>

		<listitem><para>don't prompt for a password </para></listitem>

	</varlistentry>

	<varlistentry>
		<term>ro</term>

		<listitem><para>mount read-only</para></listitem>

	</varlistentry>

	<varlistentry>
		<term>rw</term>
		<listitem><para>mount read-write</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>

	<varlistentry>
		<term>rsize</term>
		<listitem><para>default network read size</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>

	<varlistentry>
		<term>wsize</term>

		<listitem><para>default network write size</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>

	</variablelist>
</refsect1>

<refsect1>
	<title>ENVIRONMENT VARIABLES</title>

	<para>
		The variable <emphasis>USER</emphasis> may contain the username of the
person to be used to authenticate to the server.
The variable can be used to set both username and
password by using the format username%password.
	</para>
	
	<para>
		The variable <emphasis>PASSWD</emphasis> may contain the password of the
person using the client.
	</para>

	<para>
		The variable <emphasis>PASSWD_FILE</emphasis> may contain the pathname
of a file to read the password from. A single line of input is
read and used as the password.
	</para>

</refsect1>

<refsect1>
	<title>NOTES</title>
	
	<para>This command may be used only by root, unless installed setuid, in which case the noeexec and nosuid mount flags are enabled.</para>
</refsect1>

<refsect1>
	<title>CONFIGURATION</title>
		<para>
The primary mechanism for making configuration changes and for reading 
debug information for the cifs vfs is via the Linux /proc filesystem.
In the directory /proc/fs/cifs are various configuration files and
pseudo files which can display debug information.  For more
information see the kernel file fs/cifs/README
</para>
</refsect1>

<refsect1>
	<title>BUGS</title>

	<para>Passwords and other options containing , can not be handled.
For passwords an alternative way of passing them is in a credentials
file or in the PASSWD environment.</para>

	<para>The credentials file does not handle usernames or passwords with
		leading space.</para>

	<para>
Note that the typical response to a bug report is a suggestion
to try the latest version first. So please try doing that first,
and always include which versions you use of relevant software
when reporting bugs (minimum: mount.cifs (try mount.cifs -V), kernel (see /proc/version) and
server type you are trying to contact.
</para>
</refsect1>



<refsect1>
	<title>VERSION</title>

	<para>This man page is correct for version 1.0.6 of 
	the cifs vfs filesystem (roughly Linux kernel 2.6.6).</para>
</refsect1>

<refsect1>
	<title>SEE ALSO</title>
	<para>
	Documentation/filesystems/cifs.txt and fs/cifs/README in the linux kernel
	source tree may contain additional options and information.
</para>
</refsect1>

<refsect1>
	<title>AUTHOR</title>
	
	<para>Steve French</para>

	<para>The syntax and manpage were loosely based on that of smbmount. It 
		was converted to Docbook/XML by Jelmer Vernooij.</para>

	<para>The maintainer of the Linux cifs vfs and the userspace
		tool <emphasis>mount.cifs</emphasis> is <ulink url="mailto:sfrench@samba.org">Steve French</ulink>.
		The <ulink url="mailto:linux-cifs-client@lists.samba.org">Linux CIFS Mailing list</ulink> 
		is the preferred place to ask questions regarding these programs. 
	</para>

</refsect1>

</refentry>
